in this lesson we're going to talk about
how to convert a quadratic function in
standard form
to vertex form and vice versa
sometimes you may need to be able to do
this
so let's cover it in this video
and a way to do it is to use the
we need to complete the square basically
half of six is three
so we're going to add three squared to
both sides
adding it to the left side
is the same as subtracting it from the
right side
so we can add 3 squared to both sides or
we can add 9 to the right side and also
simultaneously subtract 9 from the right
side
9 and negative 9 is zero so we're not
changing the value of the right side
so let's do it that way
now let's factor x squared plus six x
plus three squared every time you
complete the square you're creating a
perfect square trinomial
and to factor it you can see everything
you need here
first it's x
and then whatever this sign is
it's plus
and then it's this number before you
square it
three
squared
outside we have negative five minus nine
so in vertex form it's x plus three
squared
minus fourteen
so we can clearly see that the vertex
is negative three negative fourteen
and we can also use this equation to
find vertex negative b over 2a
b is six
a is one negative six over two is
negative three which
confirms the x value here
now let's talk about how we can
go back
to standard form
so how can we convert this expression
which is in vertex form back to standard
form
all you need to do is expand x plus 3
squared
let's foil it x times x is x squared
x times 3 is 3x
3 times x is 3x
3 times 3 is 9.
and then combine like terms 3x plus 3x
is 6x
minus 14 is negative 5.
so this gives us
the original function in standard form
so now you know how to convert from
standard form to vertex form by
completing the square
and you know how to convert from vertex
form to standard form by expanding and
using the foil method